hi everybody welcome back to the channel
and today we're going to talk about Gua
gum
so if you've ever heard of it it's a
very common ingredient found in many
foods including ice cream
we're going to talk about
what exactly is how you use it whether
it's good for you and using it in ice
cream so stick around
[Music]
first thing is guar gum as a natural
substance it's derived from the seeds of
The Gua plant which is native to India
and Pakistan
the seeds are dehusked and then the
shells are ground into a fine powder and
the gum is extracted through process of
milling and sieving the result is an
off-white powder that is given a
descriptive name of e412 so all e
numbers are bad for you it's just made
from the ground seed casings
to our gamma's type of soluble fiber
which means that it dissolves in water
this makes it useful as a thickening
agent for stabilizers and emulsification
in lots of foods obviously ice cream
included
it is a polysaccharide which means it's
made of Two Sugars it's actually a
galactaman and polysaccharide which
means that the two sugars are galactos
and mannose
using your gum in ice cream can help
create a smooth creamy texture and it
has an effect on reducing the Ice
Crystal formation as well which is
especially useful in low-fat or
non-dairy ice creams where it can
actually help mimic the texture of dairy
ice cream
there are quite a few stabilizers that
actually do this so you might want to
try out some other options and not just
go our gum which is really best when
used with other stabilizers it's
important to note that go our gum can
withstand 80 degrees Centigrade for five
minutes before it starts to break down
and become less effective it also
creates a gel with calcium which is
ideal for us ice cream aficionados
it's absorption rate so the amount of
water that it absorbs is something we
really have to pay attention to it can
absorb up to eight times more water than
other stabilizers such as cornstarch
now onto the subject of whether girl gum
is actually good for you
now whilst it's generally considered
safe some people may have or may
experience some digestive issues when
they consume too much and that's because
it is a fiber at the end of the day
it's been used as food additive and a
lot of these people say that you need to
pay attention to your body's natural
reactions and you get that with any food
substance as well
a lot of Studies have actually found out
that guar gum can be beneficial and used
as a food for those taking probiotics
the guar gum will actually act as a
Prebiotic and help feed those probiotic
bacterias
guar gum was also used heavily excuse
the pun in weight loss programs in the
80s and that was because it had a very
quick digestive tract reaction
that means that it will absorb a massive
amount of water as it goes down at your
stomach now there were some evidence
where a lot of people would actually eat
guagan by the teaspoon and it would
block their esophagus
obviously a few people joked doing this
and that is why you are not going to
find it in weight loss programs anymore
and finally if you're going to use a
goigum in your ice cream then you need
to start looking at using low numbers
again around 0.1 percent to 0.3 percent
of your total weight of the base it does
combine really really well with locust
bean gum which has a stronger effect at
reducing Ice Crystal size in your ice
cream so that's where I would start if I
were you thank you very much for
watching if you've got this far if
you're wondering where I am I am
actually at ghost Lake in Alberta so
just have a look around here
hideous as I'm sure you'll agree
but thanks very much for watching that's
our next stabilized video we're going to
talk about locust bean gum next so
hopefully you'll stick around and we'll
see you next time
foreign